howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show this is a current episode
currents are shorter and less heavily
produced than our full-length episodes
and generally focus on a single topic as
always links to books articles and
organizations mentioned are available on
the episode page at Jim read show calm
that's Jim rut show calm on today's
currents episode we have as our guest
Brian Hanley Brian's an independent
scientist published work in economics
epidemiology and he has worked in
vaccines including virus vaccines brian
is going to talk a little bit we're
gonna discuss first the economic
consequences of lockdowns economic and
social consequences of lockdowns i.e
that is not caused free to do lock downs
and some ideas brian has on how to get
us out of lockdown as soon as possible
so Brian let's start with the costs of
lockdowns economic social other okay so
I went and looked for examples of big
drops in GDP such as we've seen during
this lockdown we hits four point three
back in April as the u.s. drop in GDP
and it took a year for the 2008 crisis
to get down that low all of the examples
that I've seen have been that will have
been not v-shaped but l-shaped there I
don't really like the word l because it
has it doesn't really describe it very
well it's a step you take a step down
and then you you can get going at the
previous rate of growth but you don't
recover what you lost so what that means
is collectively worldwide we have lost a
total of 12 GDP years
which amounts to a total it's a bits
business but it's held pretty steady at
eight trillion per year which is a total
of 96 trillion and for the u.s. itself
it's 1.8 trillion and that's a twentieth
twenty one point six almost twenty two
GDP years which is equivalent to in an
entire year's GDP since the 2008 crisis
so we have a significant GDP gross and
based on historical analysis we're not
going to get a v-shaped recovery and
best we'll get a you know
reestablishment to the firth of the
previous track but from a lower base is
that a way to say it so that night right
and going forward from from here with
the coronavirus lockdown we do not know
what it's going to be now I just I just
read it an article today an interview
with Rubini
and he's predicting an l-shaped in other
words a step for this and that it's
gonna be deep because there are there's
a lot of outstanding consumer debt and a
lot of that is in people who needed to
be working continuously so he sees this
as being as being a real problem
particularly in the US yep I agree there
will be a certainly a problem and we and
further we don't know how far down the
down leg is on the L right it could be
it could easily be fifteen or sixteen
percent not you know yes not the eight
or ten percent that you're that the date
is so far show so we have good an L down
we get a rise up and in in previous
recoveries one of the things we do know
is that the ones that are most strongly
affected are young people people first
trying to get on the career ladder
they're essentially have their heads
held down for some significant period of
time and most the analysis shows they
never catch up right because because of
all those lost opportunities going
forward that window we talked about with
the step you know you're tracking at the
same rate but you're you're you're
your you're way below what you would
have been so all those younger younger
people will not have those career tracks
and then also and I think there's
because of the fact that Sencha Lee the
economy's on hold for a while the normal
growth you'd have in your career like so
you know when you're 25 if you're good
you're rising very rapidly in your
career in the business world but if
nothing has happened nobody's getting
promoted for two years
you just lost those two years and you'll
never gain them back yeah all right so
we have a that gets clear early you have
a significant economic loss the most
likely and I think it's reasonable the
l-shaped model then at best we'll get
back on the same growth path there's
also social implications I know you've
talked a little bit about that lockdown
seems to hit be increasing the suicide
rates at least in some areas talk about
that a little bit yes yes there there's
there's reports that we have had in the
last four months roughly in the number
of suicides that are no or suicide
attempts
coming to ers that normally occur in a
full year which is an indication that
people are either psychologically
stressed or or that they are
economically stressed and they're just
saying you know I don't want to deal
with this want one of the other probably
personally I've been seeing a new crop
of what appear to be homeless people
sitting sitting around at shopping malls
and things like that and the reason that
they they don't look like they've been
homeless very long is you know they're
they're they're normally fed they don't
look there's skin ISM weather and all
the rest of it and they're and they're
all young yeah we know an awful lot what
50% of Americans approximately have less
than $500 worth of liquid financial
reserves and so yeah being out of work
for two months even at lower than
average consumption rate because that's
the only good news about this shitshow
is that our consumption rates are also
way down so we've reduced our reserves
less than otherwise what but still if
you're if your reserves 500 dollars
there's gonna be a lot of people that
are at or near the edge right now so
let's take both of those elements
potential long-term damage the economy
social costs in terms of probably mental
health either first order from the
stress of lockdown and the threat of
disease and to from the economic
consequences leading to maybe as much as
a 300% increase in suicides as long as
the lockdown occurs so if we if we
possibly going forward you know with
with the the economic stress will
continue and it will probably increase
we have never had this kind of a
dramatic job loss ever in history that
is correct for an uncharted territory
though I do have some reason to be
optimistic in that if we go back to our
teens Ian's analysis of the long-term
failure of modern modern financial
capitalism it tends to be a lack of
demand as opposed to lack of supply and
so one thing I'm looking forward that we
may have a little bit of v-shape comes
from the fact that demand is I mean yeah
demand has not been met for a long time
for instance car sales have followed by
a tremendous amount of sales when this
is over car sales I suspect will rebound
above their normal baseline for a while
there may be some other categories that
will also rebound
you know optional surgery for instance
will rebound afterwards but not for long
and maybe not enough to produce it
probably not enough to produce a v-shape
yeah that's a Rivini says yeah there'll
be an initial you an initial u-shape
start and then it'll that that will
disappear and it'll just be a no yeah
okay let's take that as a given let's
just stipulate it for what comes next
that the cost of lockdown are very
substantial economically they're very
substantial socially in terms of impact
on young people's career opportunities
and they're we pay a substantial cost in
terms of raw deaths in terms of suicide
so what's the alternative at this point
I should add that Brian is has
experience in viral
scenes including having made his own
coded 19 vaccine and had given it to
himself so with that what should we do
let me preface this by talking about
vaccines a little bit because there's
more than one type the original the
original vaccine is vaccinia which it
was the smallpox vaccine which was the
serendipitous discovery that cow pox
would if would infect humans and cause
mild disease and then those people were
protected from smallpox there haven't
been very many of those going well there
there's been as far as I know there's
been no other such vaccine since in the
50s we started developing attenuated
vaccines by passages in cell cultures
and over time those would adapt to the
cell culture and they would become mild
diseases for humans that's how we got
the measles vaccine that we use today
that's how the original Salk vaccine was
made that's also how the second so the
second vaccine was made that followed it
the problem with that type of vaccine is
it's kind of a black box and back then
we didn't do sequencing we didn't really
know how far it was away so a vaccine of
that type could potentially revert to
virulence and the Salk vaccine did that
in a very small number of cases so it we
stopped using that we created
regulations to deal with that kind of
situation we haven't updated them since
since then we've we've learned the
structure of DNA we've learned how to
sequence rapidly we we can get the
sequence for a new disease once we
identify it pretty quickly the SARS CoV
2 vaccine the Wuhan strain was sequenced
and posted by the 10th of January and
today we can use
data to rationally design vaccines
because we also understand the genes of
viruses much better so so we can go in
and we can look at that and we can make
decisions now there are several kinds of
nonliving vaccines and non-living
vaccines are inherently safer because
they're not going to cause disease
they're safe for immunocompromised
people and the the the original ones
were killed vaccines that's that's what
the current influenced your li influenza
vaccine is it's a killed vaccine so what
I'm going what I'm going to propose is
really an expansion and version of what
we already do every year to deal with
influenza the next step from kill
vaccines is you can you can take
components of the virus the proteins and
you can combine those with adjuvant and
inject those and those will create an
immune response they are pretty good at
generating antibody responses they're
fair depending on the claim of adjuvant
at generating cd8 responses cd8 T cells
are what clears a virus infection there
have been studies done in mice where if
you if you don't have the cd8 s-- you
can have any amount of antibodies those
mice will die they'll die more slowly
the more antibodies they have but they
will still die because you have to get
rid of the factories that are producing
the virus in order to defeat it and
that's what cd8 t-cells do the most
modern type of vaccine are nucleotide
vaccines of which there are two kinds
there's DNA vaccines which were invented
in the late 80s early 90s and I did a
year of my graduate school work with
Gary Rhodes who was the inventor of DNA
vaccines one of the things we discussed
was how he had never seen and basically
if you keep the design straightforward
you know keep it simple
you code for proteins that are there in
the virus natively without modifying
them or if you modify them very very
little very little you will get a
successful vaccine he had never seen an
instance where this didn't work with DNA
vaccines in this century we have
developed RNA vaccines as as a
practicality and because of the way that
they developed the technology we can
create RNA vaccines and roll them out as
fast as we can DNA vaccines but we we
can manufacture them much more quickly
you can manufacture on a tabletop for
RNA vaccines millions potentially
millions of doses which makes it some
which means that you've got something
there that scales well for roll out DNA
vaccines at this point
nobody's figure out how to make them
scale as well my my vaccine was a DNA
type vaccine I probably designed it
around the same time Moderne was
designing theirs
they had a an application into the FDA
by early February and they got approved
for a clinical trial in early March I
tested the DNA vaccine then I designed
on myself and a couple of colleagues we
were called Co developers so we did it
under self-experimentation rules and
those up you know it's certainly safe
which is you know what we expected
because there's there's very little
reason to think that you wouldn't have a
safe vaccine it appears to be effective
I've tried to well III have exposed
myself multiple times to people who were
diagnosed as sick with Kovan 19 I have
not gotten symptoms that is of course
not in itself approved because some
people a lot of people on the label that
population don't get symptoms but I am
in
the high-risk category at my age and
because I have asthma and have had it
most of my life
so with this as background what I'm
saying is there is no reason today why
we aren't rolling out vaccines like
maderas vaccine right away and do it as
a rolling as a roll out trial you
monitor it you look at it but you always
evaluate it from the point of view of we
have a disaster here essentially it
should be wartime rules not the kind of
rules you have when you're assuming that
everything has to be absolutely
perfected and all the t's crossed and
all the eyes done it because for
vaccines particularly for vaccines that
aren't alive there's very little reason
and to to think that there's going to be
a serious problem particularly in adults
now we had a previous conversation about
this topic a little side conversation
and I was kind of surprised by the data
on how many Americans have died from
vaccines since 1950 that might be an
interesting data yeah I do my best to
okay I've done my best to come up with a
number and that number is below 200 it's
probably on the order of a hundred the
majority of the real serious casualties
were in well the early ones were were
with the Salk vaccine there were
thousands of children who got polio from
it there are people who have gotten join
bar syndrome which is arguable whether
or not is related to vaccines there the
it has been accepted kind of
provisionally as possibly related to
vaccines but it's far more more common
and likely that it was related to an
actual illness with an actual virus
so bottom line is the the the risks from
modern vaccines are in terms of deaths
at least are minuscule very very low
there was a there was a an RSV vaccine
killed RSV vaccine made in the it came
out in 56 which was pulled because there
were some instances of children under
the age of 2 who appeared to have a
worse course of disease because they had
the vaccine that wasn't true for anyone
over the age of 2 so it could have been
as with some other vaccines that could
have been simply not used in children of
that age group but that kind of thing is
pretty darn rare you know there there's
the the you know the rest of it one of
the interesting things about the anti
vaccination people is that virtually all
of what they cite is just basically made
up it's not it's not real stuff or it's
wildly exaggerated so the argument is
that modern vaccines are relatively safe
but the other half of the FDA standard
for any kind of medication is that it
also be effective how would we make sure
or happen or I guess we can't make sure
that we'll be having a reasonable
confidence that these new start up
vaccines of which there's been you know
human trials on small numbers are
actually effective we don't want to
vaccinate a whole bunch of people with a
vaccine that doesn't provide actual
immunity right now there are with all
vaccines except one the smallpox vaccine
there are there's a range of immunity
that is provided by them the yearly
influenza vaccine based on epidemiology
it's estimated that somewhere around 30
percent of everyone who's vaccinated
actually gets the flu but they get such
a light case that
they don't even know it those people can
potentially infect others for a short
period of time measles vaccine which is
even the live attenuated vaccine has had
failures now some of those failures are
probably because of poor storage
conditions the the measles vaccine is
the live attenuated vaccine and if it's
not kept at the right temperature under
the right conditions and all the rest of
it it will you know it'll it'll die and
so you won't get an effective
vaccination from that there are
instances where there have been there
there have been people who were who had
the measles vaccine who were later
infected by people who didn't have it
and got measles and you know we're
spreading the virus all over now those
people were protected so in vaccinology
we talk about protection and we talk
about sterilization so as the goal is a
sterilizing vaccine and what that means
is that you will have not just cd8 T
cells but you will have high enough
antibody levels that if you get a normal
dose of the virus you'll essentially get
no no infection or there will be nothing
seen and so for example in Mouse studies
what they would do is they would and
they would expose a bunch of vaccinated
mice to a virus and then two days later
they would kill the mice and they would
look in the lungs to see if if there's
any evidence of virus in the lungs and a
really good vaccine will have no
evidence of virus in the lungs so what
what we've seen in most and most mammals
if you use a DNA vaccine or an RNA
vaccine on them they will get a they
will get a good antibody response on a
good cd8 response
for reasons that are not fully
understood when you inoculate primates
with a DNA or RNA vaccine and we are
primates is sometimes called the primate
barrier in nucleotide vaccinology you
will not get a great antibody response
you may get some but you're not going to
get a really strong one but you will get
a good cd8 t-cell response so what that
means is that the this kind of vaccine
you if is considered protective for the
individuals who get it but it may not be
sterilizing if you combine a DNA or RNA
vaccine with a later component vaccine
for it has a protein in it those are
good at generating antibody responses
and after and since the body has been
primed to respond by the DNA or RNA
vaccine it will give you a good antibody
response and something else to remember
when when I'm talking about these
rollouts is that just because you've
been inoculated was one vaccine does not
mean you can't be inoculated with
another one and that will you know
vaccinology is full of multistage
inoculations that improve the antibody
response and improve the cd8 response
each time something else to understand
is that the current regulations are
built around the the antibody response
and this is a combination of history
that that was the first thing we found
out about was antibodies and we
developed antisera and horse serum and
all those and that was a revolution of
medicine but then that hasn't been
updated and even today I run into
physicians all the time who are not
aware that antibodies don't cure a
disease that is only the cd8 t-cells to
do it so we have we have not yet adapted
the regulations
- looking at t-cell responses in people
it's a harder assay it's a much harder
SAT - to execute it's you know it's a
bunch more work so that that makes it
more expensive but it's also the measure
that really really matters for us quite
a follow-up question though if I'm
understanding you correctly and it's
quite possible that I am NOT that if we
are able to boost the cd8 t-cells
we'll keep people from getting sick but
we won't reach the herd immunity to keep
it from spreading to the whole
population
well that's see when you when you are
conducting a vaccine campaign you have
to get to 95 percent plus vaccination
rate in order to say that you have
effective herd immunity when a disease
goes through a population you have to
get to around 70 percent now why is that
the reason is that the transmission
networks through which viruses
communicate have particular pathways
they're not you know they're not
completely flat each person has you know
some people have a lot of connections
that they can transmit through most
people have very few that's why in
epidemiology nowadays r0 is not really
considered to be a proper measure
because it's basically a mathematical
fiction most transmission of disease is
done by suit what are called super
spreaders and that's true in the case of
in most diseases and that's true in the
case of this SARS CoV 2 epidemic we you
know there are some people who transmit
it to ten fifty maybe a hundred or more
the median is somewhere between zero and
one and then when you average that all
that out after the fact and look at the
curve you see something that is called
r0 but it's not it's not a it's not
something that's actually out there in
in the real world okay
that answered the question well it not
really is gonna that's aside that's a
side story cuz if you'll still get
propagation presumably back I suppose
your point is that it doesn't matter
well well well my point is that if
you're using vaccines to stop an
epidemic you either have to do ring
vaccination or you have to get ninety
five percent plus of the population
immune and as an instance of that we
don't do that
currently with influenza because
influenza is you know it's not it's not
a vaccine that everybody gets every year
and so we that's one of the reasons we
have you know between thirty and fifty
thousand people a year dying of
influenza as a normal course of events
because that's a pandemic that happens
every year we don't really pay attention
to it like we are with this one which is
the same kind of thing but at a high at
a and a higher death rate so the point
here is that what we'd want to do is we
want to protect initially like first
responders medical personnel the elderly
the people who are the most likely to
die to choose you to be exposed from it
and and potentially die and and the
people who are risking the most after
that we can you know we can roll it out
to anybody who wants it and that should
be a huge number of people now there
will be some people who won't and this
gets so so this gets to how you can say
okay we won't necessarily need to have a
lockdown because most people will be
protected who would be the ones who are
great at greatest risk and then
everybody else can potentially decide
for themselves and and so nucleotide
vaccines killed vaccines and component
protein vaccines can all contribute to
that pretty well and a combination of
those can can do really well
but if you want the most robust
long-term immunity then you want to have
some type of a live vaccine and that
would be a recombinant engineered
vaccine such as adenovirus with the
spike protein attached to it or you
would want to try to engineer a
rationally engineer a an attenuated
vaccine which could potentially be done
with this particular virus there are
some specific proteins that will for
example there's RF 3a which produces a
protein that prevents the individual
cells from producing interferon which is
one of the reasons why this virus tends
to last lasts so long because it's
stopping the body from responding to it
as effectively so can i Reese um er eyes
your strategy and and the reasoning
again and correct me if I'm wrong which
I may well be we're paying a high cost
for lockdown economically socially and
in broad s through things like suicide
driven by both stress and economic loss
modern RNA type vaccines can scale
easily are very safe surprisingly so and
are effective at at least keeping people
from getting sick through CDA t-cell
development so therefore there's no
reason we shouldn't roll those out at
scale right away presumably with least
some curation on which ones go out yeah
yeah you're gonna you're gonna want to
have you're going to want to follow it
okay as a car has a kind of trial that
but not you know currently as an example
there was a vaccine that was produced
for rotavirus by Wyeth and it had five
cases of what's called intussusception
in infants who had who had gotten it and
this is a easily treatable condition
it's where that where the small
intestine
telescopes in on itself okay and it can
be a it happens pretty regularly it's
it's it's easily treated and because of
this why it's decided to pull the
vaccine which meant that there were in
the interim years before there was a new
vaccine there were over a thousand
deaths of children in the West and
worldwide the the death toll is was over
half a million during that time and this
is and this is a readily vaccinate able
disease now that isn't that is an
example of corporate liability avoidance
because of the climate in torez vaccines
at that time which was still very you
know the the the anti vaccine people
have been astonishingly successful at
peddling their their their lies and and
juries are easily convinced so you know
we've lost the vaccines because of that
sort of thing so what I'm getting at
here is that when we do these rollouts
yes we should log things but we
shouldn't be deciding to stop because of
something like on like that because of
something that is probably unrelated it
that that that nobody in a in a military
situation would would would blink an eye
out so I think that's the fundamental
distinction yeah wartime rules we know
there's some risk they're not zero but
we're paying huge costs by not doing
anything so whatever we have to do from
a legal or administrative or
indemnification for perspective to get
it rolling we should do that's some of
your argument pretty well yeah with with
the caveat that you know the real risk
is really really low um probably it's so
close to zero that it is indecipherable
okay well I think that's been a very
interesting perspective very different
from anything we've heard from anybody
else either on this show
in general that we should take you know
some reasonably curated set of the
vaccines and just go with it accept some
risk probably very tiny and get various
benefits from either actual immunity or
at least people not getting the disease
and be able to open the economy up for
probably everybody but those in a high
risk category and though this those two
things are not different okay you can
have immunity and still get sick this
happens on a regular basis you know for
example I had I had rubella twice once
when I was a kid and once when I was in
college and the second time I got it I
had a much lighter case of the disease
but immunity does decline with time it
can also decline because for example if
somebody gets a serious case of measles
that will destroy a lot of a lot of or
all of some of their populations of
memory T cells and memory b-cells so if
they are exposed to that virus again
it's as if they had never been they had
never been exposed before got it thanks
for that clarification and thanks for
being on the show I think people will
find this an intriguing idea and maybe
the idea will get out and get thought
about seriously by those people working
on on our policy so with that thanks
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jerod Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com
[Music]